<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogdown on Paul Oldham&#39;s Analytics Blog</title>
    <link>https://www.pauloldham.net/tags/blogdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogdown on Paul Oldham&#39;s Analytics Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright @ Paul Oldham 2017-2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.pauloldham.net/tags/blogdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating A Bibliography with rcrossref</title>
      <link>https://www.pauloldham.net/creating-a-bibliography-with-rcrossref/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.pauloldham.net/creating-a-bibliography-with-rcrossref/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this article we will look at how to create a bibliography using the &lt;code&gt;rcrossref&lt;/code&gt; package in R with RStudio. To help us get started we will also look at how to reference any R packages that you use in your work with &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt;. The article is part of work in progress for the WIPO Handbook on Patent Analytics. Comments and suggestions are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of us will have spent an unreasonable amount of our time struggling to create bibliographies for a thesis, publication or reports. Software such as Endnote (Clarivate Analytics), Mendeley (Elsevier) and Zotero provide options for creating and managing bibliographic data. From experience, this generally involves masses of hours fiddling around with reference formats and so on before and after submission for publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crossref.org/&#34;&gt;Crossref&lt;/a&gt; is a non-profit organisation that provides metadata on over 96 million publications in the form of information on the authors, titles, organisations, funding and so on. It is not a full text database but is increasingly providing access to abstracts and links to full texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crossref can be accessed through an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/CrossRef/rest-api-doc&#34;&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;. For R users, Scott Chamberlain, Carl Boettiger, Ted Hart and Karthik Ram have developed the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/rcrossref&#34;&gt;rcrossref&lt;/a&gt; package as part of the ever growing suite of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;ROpenSci&lt;/a&gt; packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started we will install the packages we are going to need and then look at how to quickly create a bibliography file for packages we are going to use. Once we have a grip on that we will use &lt;code&gt;rcrossref&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;packages&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Packages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to R and RStudio then first we need to get set up. To install R for your operating system choose the appropriate option &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and install R. Then download the free RStudio desktop for your system &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/#download&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should already have knitr installed with RStudio but in the wildly unlikely event that you don’t then run this line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;knitr&amp;quot;)
install.packages(&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will use the development version of rcrossref for reasons we will explain below. You will need devtools (above) installed to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;devtools::install_github(&amp;quot;ropensci/rcrossref&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(knitr)
library(rcrossref)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;creating-a-bibliography-file&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Creating A Bibliography File&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the puzzling things about getting started with creating bibliographies in RStudio… is how to create a bibliography file. So, as a warm up let’s do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yihui Xie has made it incredibly easy to create a bibliography in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bibtex.org/&#34;&gt;bibtex&lt;/a&gt; format with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.name/knitr/&#34;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt; package. Let’s create a file that contains packages mentioned in this article. The &lt;code&gt;write_bib()&lt;/code&gt; function allows us to add in a vector of package names, and to specify the path and name for the file using &lt;code&gt;file =&lt;/code&gt;. In this case I am creating a file called packages.bib in the content section of my blogdown site. I’ll break it up for visibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;knitr::write_bib(c(&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;base&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;rcrossref&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;blogdown&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;bookdown&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;knitr&amp;quot;,
                   &amp;quot;rmarkdown&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;citr&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;bibtex&amp;quot;), width = 60, 
                 file = &amp;quot;/Users/pauloldham17inch/blog/content/post/packages.bib&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This takes citation information from the description section of the packages. When you run this chunk it is normal to see a bunch of warning messages such as &lt;code&gt;DESCRIPTION file of package ‘ggmap’could not determine year for ‘ggmap’ from package&lt;/code&gt; etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is that easy. All we need to do is identify where we want to save the file and then try to remember the packages that we use regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we take a quick look at the content we will see the following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@Manual{R-rcrossref,
  title = {rcrossref: Client for Various &amp;#39;CrossRef&amp;#39; &amp;#39;APIs&amp;#39;},
  author = {Scott Chamberlain and Carl Boettiger and Ted Hart
    and Karthik Ram},
  note = {R package version 0.8.1.9513},
  url = {https://github.com/ropensci/rcrossref},
  year = {2018},
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now we have an easy way to create a bibliography file, hurrah! Let’s move on to rcrossref.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-rcrossref-addin&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The rcrossref Addin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RStudio includes a button at the top of the screen called Addins. It’s here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.pauloldham.net/images/rcrossref/addin.gif&#34; width=&#34;400px&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard version of rcrossref includes an addin that allows you to search for references using dois (document identifiers). I’ll come back to that. However, the add in for the development version does more thanks to great work by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/haozhu233&#34;&gt;Hao Zhu&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/haozhu233/giphyr&#34;&gt;giphyr&lt;/a&gt; fame. In response to a request on github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/rcrossref/issues/148&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, Hao Zhu created a new version of the rcrossref addin that we will use now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Addins menu select Add Rcrossref Citations and a panel will open up. In the development version we can type in the name of an article and then Add to My Citations and Done when we are finished as we see in this example. I’ll look up one I can remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.pauloldham.net/images/rcrossref/addarticle.gif&#34; width=&#34;800px&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also use document identifiers. Here is one of mine on the completely bonkers subject of global climate engineering or geoengineering with doi: 10.1098/rsta.2014.0065.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.pauloldham.net/images/rcrossref/doi.gif&#34; width=&#34;800px&#34; style=&#34;display: block; margin: auto;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rcrossref add in creates a new file in your RStudio project directory (assuming you are using projects which is a very good thing), called crossref.bib. Once this file is created any time that you use the Addin it will add references rather than overwrite the file. So, this can be a very good way to build up a bibliography using rcrossref.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-citations-in-rmarkdown&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Adding citations in Rmarkdown&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add a citation, using the example above, we simply use &lt;code&gt;[@R-rcrossref]&lt;/code&gt;, as explained by Yihui &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/bookdown/citations.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Note when inserting the reference we skip the type (e.g. Manual, Article etc) at the start of the crossref.bib entry. The result will look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rcrossref &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Chamberlain et al. 2018)&lt;/span&gt; is a great package for accessing data for a bibliography or for larger scale bibliometrices. In 2014 Paul Oldham and his co-authors published an article on the completely mad subject of global climate engineering that succeeded in exciting consipiracy theorists using the #contrails and #chemtrails hashtags on twitter &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Oldham et al. 2014)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is ridiculously easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-the-bibliography&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Adding the Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have two bibliographies, one called packages.bib and one called crossref.bib. To get them to render when we knit the document (or build for blogdown or bookdown users… no knitting please) we need to put them in the header or YAML of the rmarkdown document. In all cases that looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bibliography: [packages.bib, crossref.bib]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we knit or build the document the citations will show up in the text itself and at the bottom of the document. To mark the start of the bibliography simply create a header such as &lt;code&gt;#References&lt;/code&gt; as the final line of your document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;going-further&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Going Further&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the team behind &lt;code&gt;rcrossref&lt;/code&gt; you now have over 96 million references at your finger tips. Many thanks are also due to Yihui Xie and the team behind &lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;bookdown&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;blogdown&lt;/code&gt; for their really great work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read more about bibliographies on the RStudio site &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/authoring_bibliographies_and_citations.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Yihui Xie’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.name/knitr/&#34;&gt;knitr website&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/dp/1498716962/ref=cm_sw_su_dp&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; are great resources &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Xie 2016a)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bookdown users can find more information in the electronic version of the bookdown book right &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/bookdown/citations.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Xie 2016b)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For blogdown users: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/apreshill&#34;&gt;Alison Presmanes Hill&lt;/a&gt;, a co-author of blogdown, has written a very useful guide to citations in the minimal blogdown demo &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rbind/blogdown-demo/blob/master/content/post/2017-08-28-adding-citations-to-posts.Rmd&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that I used to write this article. It covers subjects such as using &lt;code&gt;nocite:&lt;/code&gt; in your YAML to avoid academic style citations for packages in the text. In the references below you will see that there all the packages used are included but without inline citation. You will very probably want to read the excellent blogdown book &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as well &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;(Xie, Thomas, and Hill 2017)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packages to help you navigate citations include &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/RefManageR&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;RefManageR&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/crsh/citr&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;citr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/romainfrancois/bibtex&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bibtex&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/bib2df&#34;&gt;`bib2df&lt;/a&gt; you may well want to check them out. bib2df may be useful for cleaning up bibliography entries as it provides functions to convert a .bib file to a data.frame and back again.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnoteRef&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This list is not comprehensive and so if you know of any more please feel welcome to mention them below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level1 unnumbered&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;refs&#34; class=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-R-citr&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aust, Frederik. 2016. &lt;em&gt;Citr: RStudio Add-in to Insert Markdown Citations&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=citr&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=citr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-R-rcrossref&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chamberlain, Scott, Carl Boettiger, Ted Hart, and Karthik Ram. 2018. &lt;em&gt;Rcrossref: Client for Various ’Crossref’ ’Apis’&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/rcrossref&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ropensci/rcrossref&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-R-bibtex&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francois, Romain. 2017. &lt;em&gt;Bibtex: Bibtex Parser&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=bibtex&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=bibtex&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-W_McLean_2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLean, Mathew W. 2017. “RefManageR: Import and Manage BibTeX and BibLaTeX References in R.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Open Source Software&lt;/em&gt; 2 (16). The Open Journal: 338. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00338&#34;&gt;10.21105/joss.00338&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Oldham_2014&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oldham, P., B. Szerszynski, J. Stilgoe, C. Brown, B. Eacott, and A. Yuille. 2014. “Mapping the Landscape of Climate Engineering.” &lt;em&gt;Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 372 (2031). The Royal Society: 20140065–5. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1098/rsta.2014.0065&#34;&gt;10.1098/rsta.2014.0065&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-R-bib2df&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ottolinger, Philipp. n.d. &lt;em&gt;Bib2df: Parse a Bibtex File to a Data.frame&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=bib2df&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=bib2df&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-R-base&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R Core Team. 2018. &lt;em&gt;R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing&lt;/em&gt;. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.R-project.org/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.R-project.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-R-devtools&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wickham, Hadley, Jim Hester, and Winston Chang. 2018. &lt;em&gt;Devtools: Tools to Make Developing R Packages Easier&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=devtools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Dynamic_2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xie, Yihui. 2016a. &lt;em&gt;Dynamic Documents with R and Knitr&lt;/em&gt;. Chapman; Hall/CRC. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1201/b15166&#34;&gt;10.1201/b15166&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-Xie_2016&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. 2016b. &lt;em&gt;Bookdown&lt;/em&gt;. CRC Press. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1201/9781315204963&#34;&gt;10.1201/9781315204963&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-R-knitr&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. 2018. &lt;em&gt;Knitr: A General-Purpose Package for Dynamic Report Generation in R&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=knitr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ref-blogdown_2017&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xie, Yihui, Amber Thomas, and Alison Presmanes Hill. 2017. &lt;em&gt;Blogdown&lt;/em&gt;. Chapman; Hall/CRC. doi:&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1201/9781351108195&#34;&gt;10.1201/9781351108195&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing install using devtools::install_github(“ottlngr/bib2df”)&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
